Guide to the Bradford Edward Ableson Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Bradford Edward Ableson Papers
1978-2010
RG 222
Yale University Divinity School Library
11
(26 boxes)
These papers include correspondence, sermons, writings, and other documentation of the life and work of Bradford Edward Ableson, a Yale Divinity School graduate, Captain in the Chaplain Corps of the U.S. Navy, and clergyman. A prominent chaplain with a distinguished 25-year naval career, Captain Ableson provided combat ministry with Marines during Operation Desert Storm in the first Gulf War. From 1996 to 1999, he assumed Presidential Service duties as the Chaplain at Camp David, Maryland during the Clinton Administration. In 2004, he was promoted to the rank of Navy captain and assumed responsibilities as Command Chaplain of the U.S. Strategic Command.
Ableson, Bradford Edward
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Julia Tevis Narz Ableson, 2009
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
1959 Jan 2 Born in Tulsa, Oklahoma to Winston A. Ableson and Juanise Davis Ableson. Born 7 1/2 weeks prematurely, he weighed 4 pounds, 4 ounces at birth and spent 31 days in an incubator before being released from the hospital.
1977 Graduated from Charles C. Mason High School where he had played on the Mason Patriot Football team as an offensive guard.
1977-1980 Attended University of Science & Arts of Oklahoma, B.A. magna cum laude.
1980-1982 Attended Boston University School of Theology, Master of Theological Studies in Psychology and Pastoral Counseling.
1983 Attended Episcopal Theological Seminary of the Southwest, Certificate of Special Studies
1983 Death of his first wife, the former Gina Marie Benzel
1983-1985 Attended Yale University Divinity School, Master of Divinity. Received Yale's Mersick Prize for public speaking, 1985.
1984 Mar 28 Commissioned: Ensign, U.S. Navy Theological Student Program
1984-1987 Naval Reservist: Naval Chaplains School, Newport, RI, summer 1984; Recruit Training Command, San Diego, California, summer 1985; USS Lexington (AVT-16), Pensacola, Florida, summer 1986.
1985 Jun 2 Ordained Cumberland Presbyterian Church, Tulsa, Oklahoma.
1986Sep 30 Married Julia Tevis Narz of Louisville, Kentucky.
1987-1988 Naval Weapons Station, Concord, California, served as Station Chaplain and Marine Barracks Chaplain.
1988-1990 USS MARS (AFS-1), Oakland, California, served as Ship's Chaplain and took part in the Persian Gulf, Operation Earnest Will escorts.
1990-1991 Marine Aircraft Group 11, 3d Marine Aircraft Wing, FMFPac, El Toro, California, performed combat ministry, Desert Storm.
1991-1993 Marine Air Control Group 38, 3d Marine Aircraft Wing, FMFPac, El Toro, California, served as Group Chaplain for 6 fleet units homeported at Camp Pendleton, El Toro and Tustin, California.
1993-1996 Submarine Squadron 2, Groton, Connecticut, served as Squadron Chaplain for the largest submarine squadron in the Navy and as Waterfront Ministry Coordinator, Naval Submarine Base, New London.
1996-1999 Camp David, Maryland, Presidential Service.
1999 Received Doctor of Ministry degree from Columbia Theological Seminary. Recipient of Columbia's Sanders Prize for theology and Columbia's Telford Award for social justice. Dissertation: "Fields of Blood: A Theological Critique of United States Landmine Policy in Light of the 1997 Ottawa Process"
1999-2001 Chief of Chaplains Office, Washington, DC, served as Deputy Executive Assistant to the Chief of Navy Chaplains.
2000 Basic Military Free Fall Parachutist, U.S. Air Force, Colorado Springs, CO.
2001-2002 Attended United States Naval War College, Newport, Rhode Island. Received M.A. in National Security & Strategic Studies (Distinguished Graduate).
2002-2004 USS GEORGE WASHINGTON (CVN 73), Norfolk, Virginia, served as Command Chaplain. Combat operations: Operation Enduring Freedom and Operation Southern Watch, 2002.
2004-2007 United States Strategic Command, Omaha, Nebraska, served as Command Chaplain. Promoted to the rank of Navy captain, 2004..
2006 Became Episcopal priest under the Diocese of Kentucky. Priest-in-Residence at Trinity Episcopal Cathedral, Omaha
2007 Established the Bradford E. Ableson Prize for Ecclesiastical Leadership at Yale Divinity School, a commencement prize for the YDS student whose judgment and character are best suited for church leadership.
2007Jun 29 Received the Defense Superior Service Medal for Exceptionally Meritorious Service for the Armed Forces of the United States. Other awards received by Ableson during his career included three Meritorious Service Medals, four Navy & Marine Corps Commendation Medals, two Navy & Marine Corps Achievement Medals, campaign and unit award, Basic Parachutist Wings, and the Presidential Service Award.
2007-2009 Special Advisor to Command Chaplain, United States Strategic Command, Omaha, Nebraska
2008 Oct 14 Received the Lux et Veritas award from Yale Divinity School. The Lux et Veritas award is awarded to someone who has demonstrated excellence and distinction in applying the compassion of Christ to the diverse needs of the human condition through the wider church, institutional ministries, ecumenical organizations, not-for-profit organizations, government, or industry.
2008 Inducted into the University of Science & Arts of Oklahoma Alumni Hall of Fame.
2009 Feb 17 Died in Omaha, Nebraska of cancer.
2009 Sep 22 Dedication ceremony for the Bradford E. Ableson Memorial Library on the USS George Washington (CVN-73)
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the life and work of Bradford E. Ableson, distinguished Yale Divinity School alumnus and prominent U.S. military chaplain. First a Presbyterian minister and later an Episcopal priest, Ableson was decorated for his service during the Persian Gulf War and served as Command Chaplain aboard the USS George Washington aircraft carrier, one of the largest warships in the world. From 1996 to 1999 Ableson served as chaplain at Camp David during the Clinton administration, providing pastoral care to the President, his family, and support staff at the Maryland retreat. Correspondence, writings, sermons, and subject files provide detailed documentation of Ableson's thought, leadership skills, and dedication to his work. From early on in his career as a Navy chaplain, Ableson recognized the profound disconnect between Christians from the West and citizens in the Muslim world, and in the 1980s he emerged as an expert on preparing service members with knowledge and understanding that would make them respectful visitors in Muslim countries. Ableson's journal written during operation Desert Storm (1991) provides valuable documentation about the work of a chaplain in a combat setting.
Series I, Correspondence is primarily related to Ableson's work as a naval chaplain and contains letters and memos to and from the Department of the Navy and the Marines. Photocopies of letters received from President Bill Clinton and a small amount of personal correspondence with family and friends is also included. Ableson's letters to and from President Clinton, as well as photographs and a stole, were sent to the William J. Clinton Presidential Library by his family in 2009.
Series II, Writings and Notes, is divided into three subseries: School Papers, Articles and Papers, and Journal. The School Papers include class notes, final exams and term papers from Ableson's graduate work at Boston University, Yale Divinity School, Columbia Theological Seminary, and the Naval War College. The Articles and Papers include published articles and papers written primarily for military and chaplaincy publications. The Journal is comprised of the hand-written journal Ableson kept while serving as chaplain in Operation Desert Shield/Operation Desert Storm. The journal pages were removed from the original three ring binder for better preservation. Portions of Ableson's Caribbean journal and Desert Storm journal have been restricted until 2035.
Series III, Sermons and Speeches, is divided into two subseries: Chronological Sequence and Memorials. The Chronological Sequence is primarily made up of sermons given by Ableson at Camp David from 1996-1999. In addition to the typed copies of the sermons and service programs, there is also a CD which contains electronic files of the sermons. The Chronological Sequence also contains untitled and undated sermons. The Memorials include typed and handwritten memorial services conducted by Ableson. Captain Ableson did not want to have his sermons published because they were intended as oral presentations and in some cases may have contained unattributed quotations and stories. Captain Ableson realized that it would take a great deal of research to track down and provide specific attribution for these quotations and stories, and he felt it was unwise to allow publication when individuals quoted were still active. A twenty-five year restriction has been placed on any publication of the Ableson sermons; the Yale Divinity Library recognizes the value of Captain Ableson's sermons and their reflection of the context in which he delivered them, but will caution anyone who may want to publish sermons or excerpts from them in the future regarding Captain Ableson's concerns.
Series IV, Personal Items and Memorabilia includes biographical documentation arranged chronologically, military service records, awards and certificates, material from conferences and programs attended, photographs, and plaques. Of special interest in this series are Ableson's naval uniform and a handmade liturgical stole worn by him during Operation Desert Storm.
Series V, Subject Files are arranged alphabetically. These files were created by Ableson and kept as he labeled them.
Series VI, Resources contains books, pamphlets, periodicals and manuscripts written by others. The resources are organized into three general areas of interest: Naval Chaplaincy, Military, and Ministry resources. These resources have been retained as a sampling of the materials Captain Ableson used in his military and ministerial work. Other resources received with the Ableson papers have been added to the Yale Divinity Library's cataloged collection.
Series VII, Audiovisual contains primarily ministry related cassette tapes, CDs, and videotapes. Of special interest is a recording of an interview of Chaplain Ableson with Barbara Witcher of KBRT, July 4, 1992.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1980-2010
II. Writings and Notes, 1980-2002
III. Sermons and Speeches, 1987-2008
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1978-2009
V. Subject Files
VI. Resources, 1983-2008
VII. Audio-visual Material, 1984-2007
Military chaplains; Operation Desert Shield, 1990-1991 -- Personal narratives, American; Persian Gulf War, 1991 -- Personal narratives, American
- Correspondence, 1980-2010; Series I
  Arrangement
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the name of the recipient or sender other than Ableson.
  - A-Z (minor correspondence), 1984-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Ableson, Buddy, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ableson, Julia, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baker, Hannah, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Camp David, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clinton, President William J., 1998-2009 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cumberland Presbyterian Church, 1980-1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Department of the Navy, 1985-2008, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11-24)
  - Fellowship of Christian Athletes, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Holloway, Rev. Richard, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lawrence, Archie (includes article written by Lawrence about a reunion facilitated by BEA and letter to BEA's mother), 2007-2010 (Box 1, Folder 26A)
  - Lykins, James E., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Presbyterian Council for Chaplains and Military Personnel, 1984-1994 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Smith, Captain Victor H., CHC, USN, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Tanner, Rand E., 1988-1998 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - United States Marine Corps, 1989-1999 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - The White House, 1998-2009 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Yale University, 1983-1996 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Unidentified, 1997-2000 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Writings and Notes, 1980-2002; Series II
  - School Papers
    - Boston University
      - Binder of class notes, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
      - Binder of class notes, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 4-9)
    - Yale Divinity School
      - Class notes, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
      - Theology of Martin Luther Study Questions, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Christian Doctrine II class notes, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Systematic Theology class notes, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Term Papers and Final Exams, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Term Papers and Final Exams, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Columbia Theological Seminary
      - Personal statement, Term papers, 1993-1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Class notes, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - "The Chaplain as Model for Religious Ministry", 1994 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - "Theological Primer on Christian-Muslim Dialogue for Christian Chaplains in the United States Navy", 1995 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - "Theory of Ministry: Revisiting the Chaplain Model", 1996 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - "The Normative Position of Just War Thinking for American Christians", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Journal Caribbean Theology HD 644, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 9)
        Scope and Contents
        Portions of the journal are restricted until 2035
      - "Fields of Blood: A Theological Analysis of American Landmine Policy in Light of the 1997 Ottawa Process" (dissertation), 1999, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - Naval War College
      - Papers, 2001-2002, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
  - Articles and Papers
    - "It's not always fair - but it's life." Flight Jacket, Aug 1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Advanced Preparations for Short-Fused Deployments." The Navy Chaplain, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "Lest we forget the righteous gentile." Flight Jacket, Feb 1992 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "Some rules are made to be broken." Flight Jacket, Feb 1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - "Point Paper: Mid-year School Transfers of Navy Dependents Forced by Acceptance of Government Quarters", Sep 1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Articles in "The Dolphin", 1995, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - "A Time for Conversion." Joint Force Quarterly, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - "Following Seas: Crisis at Home", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Journal, 1991
    - Operation Desert Shield/Desert Storm Journal, 3-19 Jan 1991 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Operation Desert Shield/Desert Storm Journal, 21-30 Jan 1991 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Operation Desert Shield/Desert Storm Journal, 5-21 Feb 1991 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Operation Desert Shield/Desert Storm Journal, 22 Feb-10 Mar 1991 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Operation Desert Shield/Desert Storm Journal, 12-19 Mar 1991 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Operation Desert Shield/Desert Storm Journal, 21 Mar-14 Apr 1991 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Operation Desert Shield/Desert Storm Journal, 16 Apr-12 May 1991 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Sermons and Speeches, 1987-2008; Series III
  - Chronological Sequence
    - The Bread of Life, 14 Jun 1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - The Christmas Message, 24 Dec 1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Antidote is God, 14 Jun 1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Give to Caesar that which is Caesar's, 03 Mar 1991 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Easter Reflection, 31 Mar 1991 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - USMC/USN Chapel program, 28 Apr 1991 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - The Enemies of Jesus Wanted to Entrap Him, 18 Jun 1995 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - CD of Camp David Sermons, 1996-1999 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - The David Mentality, 16 Jun 1996 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Not All Seeds Grow, 14 Jul 1996 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Weeds in the Flowers, 21 Jul 1996 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Fed Through Compassion, 04 Aug 1996 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Water Over the Bow, 11 Aug 1996 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Good Results from Bad Intentions, 18 Aug 1996 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - From Big House to Dog House, 01 Sep 1996 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - What Do I Owe You?...And Other Hard Questions, 08 Sep 1996 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - The Choice that Heals, 15 Sep 1996 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Bean Counters Beware, 22 Sep 1996 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Great Law, Greater Grace, 06 Oct 1996 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Does God Audit?, 20 Oct 1996 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Love Within the Zip Code, 27 Oct 1996 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Buried Treasure, 10 Nov 1996 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Some Dates Don't Wait, 17 Nov 1996 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Sheep, Goats, and Other Options, 24 Nov 1996 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - One Turned Back, 28 Nov 1996 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - The Race with Grace, 01 Dec 1996 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - A Desert Pit Stop, 08 Dec 1996 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Marked for Life, 15 Dec 1996 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - The Old Familiar Story, 24 Dec 1996 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Room for Everyone, 29 Dec 1996 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Clueless at Christmas, 05 Jan 1997 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Waiting for this Moment, 28 Sep 1997 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Commissioning Ceremony, Ensign Mark Whittaker, U.S. Navy, 01 Oct 1997 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - To Speak for God, 05 Oct 1997 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - The First Steps after Healing, 26 Oct 1997 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Disorganized Religion, 02 Nov 1997 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Kings are Un-American, 23 Nov 1997 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Straight Shooter, 07 Dec 1997 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Body Language, 14 Dec 1997 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Three Kinds of Givers, 21 Dec 1997 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Christmas Eve, 24 Dec 1997 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Dropped through the Cracks, 29 Dec 1997 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Reflected Glory, 04 Jan 1998 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - What Kind of Baptism?, 11 Jan 1998 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - For the Joy of It, 18 Jan 1998 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - One for All, 25 Jan 1998 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Focus After the Fact, 22 Feb 1998 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Neon not Required, 01 Mar 1998 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Affirmative Commands in the Old Testament, 18 Mar 1998 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - When Nothing is the Wrong Answer, 15 Mar 1998 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Peace Movement, 17 May 1998 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Obnoxious Religion, 15 Feb 1998 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Welcome Tells the Story, 14 Jun 1998 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - One for All, 03 Jan 1999 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - High Noon in the Holy Land, 7 Mar 1999 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - A Play in Six Acts, 14 Mar 1999 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Wake Up Lazarus, 21 Mar 1999 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Both Ends of the Road, 28 Mar 1999 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - No Dead End, 04 Apr 1999 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Unlocked for Service, 11 Apr 1999 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - The Road to Recognition, 18 Apr 1999 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Jesus at the Gate, 25 Apr 1999 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - The Road to Royalty, 02 May 1999 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - The Spirit Factor, 09 May 1999 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - The Sign of Glory, 23 May 1999 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Left Adrift, 30 May 1999 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Memorial Day, 30 May 1999 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Run of the Mill Greatness, 27 Jun 1999 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Camp David - Evergreen Chapel Programs, 1 Oct 1995, 16 Jun 1996-28 Dec 1997 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Camp David - Evergreen Chapel Programs, 4 Jan 1998 -27 Jun 1999 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Chief of Chaplains Prayer Breakfast Speech Faith that Makes a Difference, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Poem / prayer, most likely presented at Navy function in DC, 2008 (Box 8, Folder 7A)
      BEA reflects on his illness.
    - Happy Birthday, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - It was High Noon in the Middle East, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - There's a lot of Darkness in the World..., n.d. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - The Tyranny of Fairness, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - What's a Wretch Like Me Doing in a Place Like This, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Genesis 16:1-6, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Judges:4-6, 16-22, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - 1 Sam 17:32-37, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - 2 Kings 5:1-, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - 2 Kings 5:1-9, Luke 5:12-1, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Psalms 59:16-17, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Psalms 92:1-4, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Ecclesiastes 2:14-15, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Isaiah 1:1, 10-20, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Isaiah 11:1-10, Matthew 3:1-12, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Isaiah 30:19-21, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Isaiah 49:1-7, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Isaiah 63:16-64:8, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Matthew 3:13-17, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Matthew 4:1-11, Luke 4:1-13, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Matthew 5:1-12, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Matthew 20:1-15, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Matthew 22:37-40, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Matthew 25:14-30, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Matthew 27:46, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Mark 6:7, Psalms 16, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Mark 6:17-29, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Mark 8:27-38, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Luke 2.1 ff, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Luke 4:1-13, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Luke 9:18-25 (missing pp.2-4), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - Luke 10:25, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Luke 11:1-13, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Luke 12:29-31, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - Luke 14:1, 7-4, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - Luke 20:27-38, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Luke 23:33-43, Colossians 1:11-20, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - John 1., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - John 2:1, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - John 2:13-16, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - John 3:1-17, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - John 9:1-41, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Acts 7:54-60, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Acts 16:9-15, Revelation 21:10, 22-22:5, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Romans 4:13-17, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Philippians 4:13, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - 2 Thessalonians 3:6-13, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - 1 Peter 1:3-9, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - 2 Peter 3:8-14, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - 2 Peter 16-21, Matthew 17:1-9, Psalms 2:6-11, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - 1 John 3:1-2, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Sermons, no title, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 15-20)
    - Partial Sermons and Notes (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Sermon - Illustrations, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Sermon Notes, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Sermon Ideas, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Ordination - Ferrol, Ruben, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Retirement Speech for MSCS (SS/DV) Mark Martin, USN, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Retirement Speech for EOCS (SCW) John T. Morris, USN, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - More than Conquerors, Virginia Military Institute Memorial Chapel Service, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Speeches, no title, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Memorials
    - Deborah Lee House, 31 Aug 1992 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - LCDR Elliot F. Larose, USN (Ret.), 10 Sep 1993 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Luke Gregory Martin, 29 Jul 1998 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Barbara Vorenkamp, 16 Sep 1998 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Buddy Ableson (BEA's Father), 04 Dec 1999 (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Reflections on Captain Schirra, 21 May 2007 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - A Celebration of Life, RDML Charles Henry Griffiths, Jr., 14 Mar 2008 (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Rose Alice Ball, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - CPO David Caraway, U.S. Navy, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - A Tribute to Paul Edward Davis (BEA's Uncle), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - SGT John Mory, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - SGT Tony Smith, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 41)
    - Jamie, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 42)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1978-2009; Series IV
  - Biographical Documentation
    - Chronological Sequence
      - Transcripts, 1978-2005 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Curriculum Vitae, 1982-2002 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Naval Chaplains School, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Yale University Commencement Program, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 4)